Hello!
The first thing that you have to do to write an essay is figure out what your purpose is.
Purpose is very important.
The purpose of the essay would be the aim of the essay or the plan of the essay.
For instance if you're doing this for a professor or a high school teacher and they're telling you to write an imforative essay and you write a perssuasive.
As far as me being an English teacher for 20 years, I would have given an F to that student.
Purpose is so important.
If you don't meet your purpose, nothing else matters.
Let me give you an example of what I'm talking about.
If you were to write and imformative essay on say a historical figure and you pick Abraham Lincoln and you write the paper on how he was not an effective president, you purpose is lost; you're pursuading.
You must fit your purpose in right, and usually the essays are pursuasive or an informative.